UTKARSH GARG

Tech Lead

utkarsh22garg@gmail.com | +91 - 7753839036 | LinkedIn | Medium

SUMMARY

Full-Stack developer with **4.5+** years of professional experience, specializing in **TypeScript, ReactJS,** and **NodeJS.** Core contributor to business intelligence tools and logging micro-services, achieving significant performance improvements and scalability. Proven track record in mentoring, component library development, and data visualization. Recognized for significant performance improvements and effective data visualization solutions.

EXPERIENCE

Tech Lead, D. E. Shaw & Co.

July 2020 - Current

Hyderabad, India

Member of the Web Infrastructure team, contributing to scalable frontend and backend development. Focuses on enhancing business intelligence tools, improving UI component libraries, optimizing performance, and mentoring team members.

- Developed and maintained a comprehensive business intelligence tool using TypeScript, ReactJS, and Storybook.
- Implemented a robust Logger micro-service API with **NodeJS**, optimizing endpoints for large batched requests and effective data retrieval.
- Created a usage logging insights tool in JavaScript and Python, aiding in data-driven decision making.
- Increased data processing efficiency by 12x by integrating Dask for paralleldistributed computing in backend analytics.
- Led the redevelopment of the **React** UI component library on **Material UI** and improved component development methodology.
- Owned and maintained five projects to keep them updated and made sure developers use these modules without any hassle.
- Actively participated in talent acquisition, interviewing candidates at IITs and contributing to the off-campus recruitment program.

Placement Coordinator, NIT Allahabad

July 2019 - May 2020

Prayagraj, India

- Conducted Mock tests and interviews to prepare students for college placements and internships.
- Organized various training sessions and PPT's of several firms for crowd of 300-400 students.
- Handled various logistics with the help of my team and made sure recruitment session by a company are organized successfully from start to end.

Summer Intern, Visa Inc.

May 2019 - July 2019

Bangalore, India

Contributed to the development and maintenance of a status tracker using **ReactJS** and **Redux**, with backend support via **GoLang** and relational database design.

- Improved SDLC process by creating a status tracker, replacing the outdated email tracking method.
- Created GoLang endpoints to fetch and update tracker configuration and data.

EDUCATION

Motilal Nehru National Institute of Technology (NIT) Allahabad

Bachelor of Technology, Computer Science & Engineering.

2016-2020

CGPA - 9.16/10

PROJECTS

Chat Encrypter

Oct 2018

Java, Cryptography, Socket Programming

- Chat Application with end-to-end symmetric and asymmetric encryption with file transfer facility.
- GitHub Link: https://github.com/utkarsh22garg
 /ChatEncrypter

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

- Promoted to Senior member
 Technical in 1.5 years for being a star performer in D.E. Shaw.
- Awarded Merit Scholarship award for standing in top 18 out of 176 students in academics during the college.
- Secured global rank 317 out of 10000+ participants in January long challenge 2019 conducted by CodeChef.
- Secured a position in top 5 out of 31 teams in annual android event DROIDRUSH conducted by MNNIT Allahabad.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: JavaScript, TypeScript, Python, C, C++, Java, HTML, CSS, SQL

<u>Libraries & Frameworks:</u> NodeJS, ReactJS, Redux, react-query, Material-UI, Python-Dask, React Testing Library, Mocha, Storybook

<u>Tools & Software:</u> JupyterLab, Visual Studio Code, Linux, Git